# LAXMIKANT LP PATHADE

http://laxmikantpathade.com • (315)560-8200 • lpathade@syr.edu 4-023, Center for Science and Technology, Syracuse University, Syracuse NY 13244

### Profile

Resourceful materials researcher with 8+ years of training, 4+ years of facility administrator experience, problem-solving skills, exceptional work-ethic, team player with strong written and oral communications skills.

Skilled in materials research, electron microscopy (certification), structural characterization, spectroscopy, computational analysis, technical softwares, & computers.

### EDUCATION

Syracuse University 2013-2018

Ph.D. Candidate in *Materials Chemistry* with Prof. Mathew M. Maye

Thesis: Internal Morphology & Corrosion Resistance in Stainless Steel Nanoparticles

### Institute of Chemical Technology, Mumbai

B.Tech. in Organic Colorant Technology; Minors in Chemical Engineering

### Work & Research Experience

## Materials Chemistry Intern at Pelitex Inc.

2017

2009-2013

- Executed a synthesis scale-up & technology transfer project for a Fortune 500 chemical company in record time.
- Designed new synthesis and safety protocols for materials synthesis at increased scales and improved waste recycling.
- Collaborated with researchers to optimize the silica shell coating to improve hydrophilicity of products.

### X-ray Facility Administrator at Syracuse University

2014-present

- Trained new users on the diffractometer and necessary safety protocols; coordinated user queue.
- Collaborated with internal & external users for specialized sample prep & data analysis.
- Scheduled maintenance & regulatory inspections. Maintained auxiliary chiller operations & repaired minor breakdowns.

### Graduate Researcher at Syracuse University

2013-present

- Investigated synthetic design of transition metal nanoparticles (NPs) that exhibited hollow internal microstructures.
- Successfully exploited our findings to improve corrosion resistance in these NPs and create truly "stainless" nanoparticles.
- Published 6 peer reviewed journal articles, co-authored 2 patents, and presented research in several professional conferences.
- Explored other research topics including asymmetric internal voids in novel NP systems, silica coating & surface functionalization of magnetic NPs, reaction monitoring using CsPbX<sub>3</sub> perovskites, & corrosion in metallic thin films.
- Received the Graduate Teaching Mentor Award in 2015 from the graduate school at SU.

#### Internships

- Interned at 2 medium-sized pigment-manufacturing plants in Mumbai industrial area. Reviewed unit operations of chemical engineering and authored a report on manufacturing efficiency & workplace safety.

  2012
- Summer research intern at ICT Mumbai; performed systematic study to synthesize an organic dyestuff intermediate. 2011

### TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Synthesis: Nanoparticles (Transition and Noble Metals, Perovskites, Quantum Dots) · Air-free Techniques (Schlenk Line and Glovebox) · Organic Lab work
- Electron Microscopy: JEOL JEM 2100FE HRTEM equipped with Gatan Orius & OneView cameras, STEM detectors, & Oxford Instruments X-Max<sup>N</sup> EDS detector (full user on 3 different JEOL TEMs & trained new users) · SEM (JEOL IT100LA) · EDS Certification from Oxford Instruments · AFM (Bruker Innova)
- Structural Characterization: Powder and Single Crystal X-ray Diffraction (Facility Manager)
- Spectroscopy: X-Ray Photoelectron Spectroscopy (XPS/ESCA) · NMR · FTIR · UV-Vis · Photoluminescence (PL)
- Technical Misc.: Photolithography · Spin coater · Sputter coater · Thermo-gravimetric Analysis (TGA) · Differential Scanning Calorimetry (DSC) · Magnetization in materials · Cyclic Voltammetry · Dynamic Light Scattering (DLS)
- Computational Analysis: Discrete Dipole Approximation (DDA) · Familiar with FDTD
- Softwares: Origin · Plotly · ImageJ · ChemDraw · Vesta · TEMCON (JEOL) · Digital Micrograph (Gatan) · AZtec (Oxford Instruments) · Bruker Diffrac.Suite · CasaXPS · Illustrator · Corel-Draw · Maya (basics) · Tinkercad
- Languages & Computer Misc.: 3D-printing · Raspberry Pi · Python · Jekyll · Wordpress · HTML · git · IATEX